Finding Aid for Douglas M. Haller papers, 1978-2011
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Douglas M. Haller papers 1978-2011, 1979-1982
Haller, Douglas M.
1 oversize folder
1 linear foot
2011138 Aa 2; Ac
Archivist and information officer active in numerous Gay/Lesbian organizations, notably the Association of Suburban People (ASP). The collection relates primarily to Haller’s activities with the Association of Suburban People and includes membership materials, executive board minutes and agendas, reports of the information officer, published material, and files relating to the organization’s political action committee.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was the gift of Douglas M. Haller (donor no. 10633 ) and came to the library in September 2011.
Periodic additions to the records are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Douglas Haller was elected (1980-1981) as one of five officers who formed the Executive Board of the Association of Suburban People (ASP), at that time the largest Gay/Lesbian social and political organization in the State of Michigan. Over 200 members were drawn from metropolitan Detroit, including neighboring Canada. As Information Officer, he delivered oral reports to the membership at the (twice monthly) general meetings concerning important occurrences in the local, national, and international Gay communities by condensing information from Gay Community News (Boston), the Advocate (San Francisco), The Washington Blade, and The New York Times. For the Detroit Free Press and the Detroit News, as well as other Gay and non-Gay periodicals, he appointed monitors to submit news items for analysis, comment, and occasional written response. Haller was also responsible for the organization's official correspondence, such as a letter to Time magazine rebutting its anti-Gay article (Mar 24, 1980) concerning William Friedkin's film Cruising. As an outgoing officer, Haller prepared an annual report recommending improvements for the organization's effectiveness, including a name change that would reflect commitment to Gay rights and capitalize upon its location in the sixth largest urban center in the United States. The organization later became the Southeast Michigan Gay and Lesbian Association. Many of its goals and functions were later subsumed into the Michigan Organization for Human Rights and eventually into the Triangle Foundation.
As a member of ASP Political Action Committee (ASP--PAC), Haller aided the National Convention Project (Washington, DC) in its goal of electing pro-Gay delegates to the Democratic National Convention and securing a Gay civil rights plank in the party platform. During the Nov., 1980 Presidential election, Haller joined the Michigan Democratic Party, serving as an Edward M. Kennedy delegate at the 17th District Presidential Sub-caucus which elected delegates for the national convention. Here helped secure the 17th District's endorsement of the historic plank eventually adopted by the Democratic Platform Committee.
The Douglas M. Haller papers reflect mainly to his activities as Information Office and executive board member of the Association of Suburban People in the period of 1978-1982. The collection, arranged and described by the donor, consists of the following series: Biographical / Personal; ASP members and general; ASP newsletters, events and publicity; ASP Executive Board; Information Officer's Reports/General Meetings; Periodical Clippings & Information; Information Officer's Correspondence, Related Publications; Political Action Committee (ASP/PAC); Michigan Democratic Party; and ASP Related and Successor Organizations.
Subjects:
Haller, Douglas M.; Association of Suburban People.; Gay liberation movement--Michigan.; Gay men--Michigan.; Gay rights--Michigan.; Gays--Michigan.; Lesbians--Michigan.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- Biographical / Personal
  - ASP Records Inventories, Haller, Douglas M. (Box 1)
  - Extracts from Personal Calendars 1979-1982 re: ASP, Gaylife, Related Events (Box 1)
  - Gay Community Service Resume (Draft) 1994 (Box 1)
  - Curriculum Vitae and Resume 2011 (Box 1)
- Members & General
  - ASP Charter and Miscellaneous (D.H. Membership July 1979-March 1982), Membership Brochures, Stationery, Button (Box 1)
  - ASP Membership Directories 1980 /Members' Addresses & Directions (Box 1)
  - ASP Members
    - General: Doyle, John S.; Embury, Philip H.; Gollis, Allan; Kieselhorst, Timothy; Piontkowsky, David: Sendler, Allen; Smart, Doug; Smith, Robert J. "Bob;" Thompson, William "Bill" (d. 1994, 56 years old) (Box 1)
    - Childers, Jim (Box 1)
    - Dennis, J. Douglas "Doug" (Box 1)
    - Fadiga, George M. (1954-2000) & Gervasi, Thomas M. (ASP Member) (Box 1)
    - Greene, Phil (a.k.a. Ojibway, Phillip/"Phil") (Box 1)
    - Horne, Ernest "Ernie" (1926-2010) (Box 1)
    - Martin, Frank (1938-2010) & Vezza, Alvin "Al" (Box 1)
    - Messer, Henry D. & House, Carl A. (Box 1)
    - Musick, William C. "Bill" & McGirr, Michael "Mike" (Box 1)
    - Pomann, James "Jim" (d. 199,3 45 years old) (Box 1)
    - Re, Robert (Box 1)
    - Redner, Alan A. (1948-1993) & DeLisa, Joseph M. "Joe" (Box 1)
    - Sivil, Daniel R. "Dan" (1940-1993) (Box 1)
    - Squires, Gary M. (Box 1)
    - Van Hoose, Charles "Chuck" (Box 1)
    - Young, David (Box 1)
  - ASP Members Photographs: Douglas Haller, Alan Redner, Frank Martin, Jim Childers, David Young, David McLaren, George Fadiga (Box 1)
- Newsletters, Events & Publicity
  - ASP Newsletters 1979-1982 (Box 1)
    (Removed to printed materials for separate cataloging)
  - ASP Eventers & Publicity
    - 1979-1980 (Box 1)
    - 1980, "Billy Budd" Opera at Masonic Auditorium (Box 1)
    - 1981, "Bent" Performances at the Attic Theatre & San Francisco Gay Men's Chorus at Ford Auditorium (Box 1)
    - 1981-1982 (Box 1)
  - ASP T-Shirts (Box 1)
- ASP Executive Board
  - ASP Officers' Annual Reports 1979-1980 (Sivil, Musick, Martin, Childers, McGirr) (Box 1)
  - ASP Executive Board Meetings
    - Agendas & Minutes, Correspondence 1980 (Box 1)
    - Agendas & Minute,s 1981, Officers' Annual Reports (Martin, Dennis, Haller, Smith) (Box 1)
- Information Officer's Reports/General Meetings
  - ASP General Meeting
    - Political Workshop, MI Democratic Party January 13, 1980 (Box 1)
    - Information Officer's Report May 25, 1980 (Box 1)
    - Arthur C. Warner Lecture & Paper Authored July 13, 1980 (Box 1)
  - Material Collected at June 29, 1980 San Francisco Gay Freedom Day Parade & Celebration (Discussed & Circulated at an ASP General Meeting) (Box 1)
  - 1980 San Francisco Gay Freedom Day Celebration (SF & LA Programs & Buttons Collected) (Box 1)
  - ASP General Meeting, Information Officer's Report
    - August 24, 1980 (Box 1)
    - September 28, 1980 (Box 1)
    - October 12, 1980 (Box 1)
    - October 26, 1980 (Box 1)
    - November 9, 1980 (Box 1)
    - November 23, 1980 (Box 1)
    - December 14, 1980 (Box 1)
    - January 11, 1981 (Box 1)
    - January 25, 1981 (Box 1)
    - February 8, 1981 (Box 1)
    - February 22, 1981 (Box 1)
    - March 8, 1981 (In Absentia) (Box 1)
    - March 22, 1981 (Box 1)
    - April 5, 1981 (Box 1)
    - May 3, 1981 (ASP Elections) (Box 1)
    - May 17, 1981 (Box 1)
    - Jun 7 1981 (Family Protection Act) (Box 1)
- Periodical Clippings & Information
  - Detroit Newspaper Articles Re: Homosexuality, Politics & Related Issues June-October 1981 (Box 1)
  - Other Newspaper Articles
    - Homosexuality, Politics & Related Issues March 1980-December 1981 [Washington Blade, NY Times, Advocate, Gay Community News, SF Examiner & Chronicle] (Box 1)
    - Gay/Lesbian Archives/Art (1980-1981) (Box 1)
    - Homosexuality, Politics, History Etc. (Advocate May-November, 1981) (Folder 1)
  - Detroit Area/Michigan Gay Material 1978-1981
    - Detroit Gaylife Newspaper and Magazine Clippings
      - "Gay Life in a Blue Collar Town," 1978 (Box 1)
      - "Why Gay History," 1978 (Box 1)
      - "Behind the Closet Door: The Hidden Lives of Detroit's Gays," 1981 (Box 1)
  - Detroit Area/Michigan Gay Material (1978-1981)
    - Palmer Park
      - "The Palmer Park Mystique," 1981 (Box 1)
      - "Palmer Park, Palmer Park," 1981 (Box 1)
    - Alternative Health Center (Gigi's Bar; Holy Trinity Family Center Benefits) (Box 1)
    - Committee on Gay Men and Lesbian Women of the ACLU of MI (Box 1)
    - Entertainment/Businesses
      - Carousel Lounge, Grand Rapids (Box 1)
      - Central Methodist Church Film, Detroit (Box 1)
      - Interchange Bar, Detroit (Box 1)
      - Leather Hut, Detroit (Box 1)
      - Selectmen of Detroit (Outlaw Bar, Detroit) (Box 1)
    - Lesbian-Gay Pride Week 1981 (Box 1)
    - Lesbians/Womyn (Box 1)
    - Motor City Business Forum Interim (First) Referral Directory 1980 (Box 1)
- Information Officer's Correspondence, Related Publications
  - Letter to Time re: the William Friedkin Film "Cruising" Apr, 1980 (Box 1)
    (the file includes a copy of the novel Cruising by Gerald Walker (New York: Bantam Books, 1980 2nd printing))
  - Letter to/Response from Jonathan Katz re: Gay American History and Career Opportunities in Gay History, March-April 1980 (Box 1)
  - Book Review by D. Haller of The Passionate Eye: The Life of William R. Valentiner by Margaret Sterne (Detroit: Wayne State University Press, 1981) (Box 1)
    (includes material related to Detroit Institute of Arts' Director Valentiner's homoeroticism)
- Political Action Committee (ASP/PAC)
  - ASP/PAC
    - 1979 (Box 1)
    - 1980 (Box 1)
    - 1981 (Box 1)
- Michigan Democratic Party
  - MI Democratic Party 1980 (November 1980 Carter/Reagan Presidential Election)
    - Membership, MI Democratic Party (Box 1)
    - "MI Democrat" Apr-December 1980 (Box 1)
    - Democratic National Convention Lesbian/Gay Rights Platform Plank Unanimous Endorsement (Box 1)
    - Jerry Brown Presidential Candidate (Box 1)
    - William M. Brodhead for Congress Material (Box 1)
    - Senator Don Riegle Special Report (Box 1)
    - John Anderson/National Unity Campaign Flyer (Box 1)
    - Ronald Reagan Material (Box 1)
    - ERA button/sticker (Box 1)
    - Wayne County General Election Ballot November 4, 1980 (Box 1)
    - Americans for Democratic Action 1979 Legislative Ratings (Box 1)
    - UAW Endorsements (Box 1)
    - Primary Election Analysis by Popular Vote & Delegates NY Times, April 1980 (Box 1)
  - MI Democratic Party 1980 (November, 80 Presidential Election)
    - President Carter/Walter F. Mondale Material (Box 1)
    - Senator Edward M. Kennedy Material (Box 1)
    - 17th District Democratic Party (Box 1)
    - Kennedy Presidential Delegate Selection Sub-caucus Membership (Box 1)
    - Kennedy Obituaries 2009 (NY Times, Le Figaro, Le Monde, Human Rights Campaign) (Box 1)
  - Michigan Democratic Party 1981-1982
    - Membership, MI Democratic Party (Box 1)
    - "MI Democrat," March-July 1981, January, 1982 (Box 1)
    - 17th District Democratic Party (Box 1)
    - Congressman Brodhead, Senator Riegle, Senator Carl Levin Reports (Box 1)
- ASP Related and Successor Organizations
  - MOHR (MI Organization for Human Rights) 1980-1981 (Box 1)
    (includes Coalition to Save the Detroit Human Rights Ordinance flyer)
  - SEMGLA (Southeast Michigan Gay & Lesbian Association; successor to ASP) circa 1986-1988 (Box 1)
  - Triangle Foundation (Jeffrey Montgomery, Sean Kosofsky) 1998-2001, 2008 (Box 1)
    (the file includes a membership pin)
Related Material
ASP newsletters found in the Haller collection have been removed and added to the library's holdings of the organization's newsletters.